<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Manage projects</title>
<date>2021-08-05</date>
</info>
<simpara>You can modify some key settings for individual projects by modifying each project’s <literal>dfx.json</literal> configuration file.
You can use the <literal>dfx config</literal> command to change these settings programmatically or manually edit the <literal>dfx.json</literal> file directly.</simpara>
<section xml:id="_how_to_change_your_source_directory">
<title>How to change your source directory</title>
<simpara>Before you compile source code for your project using the <literal>dfx build</literal> command, you might want to check the default location for storing the source code for your program.
By default, the name you use to create a new project is the name used for one data smart contract canister (<literal>canister_name</literal>) and one assets canister (<literal>canister_name_assets</literal>), and program source code is expected to be in the <literal>src/canister_name</literal> directory. Similarly, the default location for front-end source code is in the <literal>src/canister_name_assets/src</literal> directory and front-end output is located in the <literal>dist/canister_name_assets</literal> directory.</simpara>
<simpara>Depending on your application&#8217;s complexity and architecture, however, you might want to modify the default location for the program source code, the front-end source code, or front-end output.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, for a simple program, you might want to eliminate one directory level and place the source code in the <literal>src</literal> directory:</simpara>
<programlisting language="text" linenumbering="unnumbered">  "main": "src/main.mo",</programlisting>
<simpara>For more complex applications, you might want to use a multi-tiered directory structure:</simpara>
<programlisting language="text" linenumbering="unnumbered">"canisters": {
  "profiles": {
    "main": "src/profiles/utils/main.mo"
  },
  "events": {
    "main": "src/events/calendar/main.mo"
  },
  "media": {
    "main": "src/events/reports/main.mo"
  }
}</programlisting>
<note>
<simpara>If you modify the default settings for a source code directory, be sure that the settings in the <literal>dfx.json</literal> configuration file match the directory location on the file system.</simpara>
</note>
</section>
<section xml:id="_how_to_change_the_main_program_file_name">
<title>How to change the main program file name</title>
<simpara>Before you compile source code for your project using the <literal>dfx build</literal> command, you should verify the location and file name used for your program’s source code.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, if you want to build a smart contract canister for the <literal>factorial</literal> program and the source code for the program is located in <literal>src/math/factorial.mo</literal>, you should be sure that you have the correct
path specified for the <literal>main</literal> setting in the <literal>canisters</literal> section of the configuration file.</simpara>
<simpara>For example:</simpara>
<programlisting language="json" linenumbering="unnumbered">"main": "src/math/factorial.mo",</programlisting>
<simpara>Keep in mind that changing the configuration setting for the program file name only affects where the <literal>dfx build</literal> command looks for the source code to compile. Making changes in the configuration file does not rename any files or directories on the file system.
If you change the path to the main program file or the name of the file itself, be sure to change the name and location within your project directory.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_how_to_change_the_location_for_serving_the_application_front_end">
<title>How to change the location for serving the application front-end</title>
<simpara>You can change the default host name and port number for serving the application front-end by modifying the local network settings in the <literal>dfx.json</literal> configuration file.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, you can change the IP address for the local network by modifying the <literal>bind</literal> setting:</simpara>
<programlisting language="json" linenumbering="unnumbered">"networks": {
  "local": {
    "bind": "192.168.47.1:8000",
    "type": "ephemeral"
  }
}</programlisting>
</section>
</article>