<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Tutorials</title>
<date>2021-08-05</date>
</info>
<simpara>The <link xl:href="../quickstart/quickstart-intro.xml">Quick start</link> provided a simplified introduction to the basic work flow for creating and deploying a new project without exploring the contents of the project directory or sample code.</simpara>
<simpara>Next, we’ll explore writing a few simple programs to give you hands-on experience creating programs that run on the {IC}.</simpara>
<note>
<simpara>Most of these tutorials illustrate how to write programs using the {proglang} programming language.
For additional examples of programs written in other languages, see the {company-id} <link xl:href="https://github.com/dfinity/examples">examples</link> repository.</simpara>
</note>
<simpara>The following tutorials introduce the basics for writing programs that run on the {IC}:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/explore-templates.xml">Explore the default project</link> takes a closer look at the work flow for creating projects by exploring the default files and folders that are added to your workspace when you create a new project.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/define-an-actor.xml">Query using an actor</link> highlights how to replace the typical <literal>print</literal> function usually defined in a "Hello, World!" program by defining an actor (object) with a <literal>hello</literal> function.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/hello-location.xml">Pass text arguments</link> introduces different ways you can pass arguments to a function using the command-line in a terminal shell.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/counter-tutorial.xml">Increment a natural number</link> guides you through the process of writing a program that creates an actor with functions to increment and return the value of a counter.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/calculator.xml">Use integers in calculator functions</link> shows you how to write a simple calculator program for more practice working with {proglang} and to learn more about how you can customize your project environment.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/phonebook.xml">Import library modules</link> illustrates how to import and use a few basic {proglang} base library functions for working with key-value pairs in a list.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/multiple-actors.xml">Use multiple actors</link> describes how to include multiple unrelated actors in a single project to illustrate how you can compile multiple canisters for the same project.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/custom-frontend.xml">Customize the front-end</link> illustrates using a simple React framework to create a new front-end for the default sample program and guides you through some basic modifications to customize the interface displayed.
If you already know how to use CSS, HTML, JavaScript, and React or other frameworks to build your user interface, you can skip this tutorial.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/my-contacts.xml">Add a stylesheet</link> illustrates how to add a stylesheet when you use React to create a new front-end for your project.
If you already know how to add stylesheets to React, you can skip this tutorial.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/intercanister-calls.xml">Make inter-canister calls</link> illustrates how to make simple calls to functions defined in one canister from another canister in the same project.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/scalability-cancan.xml">Create scalable apps</link> describes using multiple canisters to create applications that scale.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/access-control.xml">Add access control with identities</link> describes how to create and switch between multiple user identities.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><link xl:href="tutorials/simple-cycles.xml">Accept cycles from a wallet</link> illustrates how to accept cycles sent from the default wallet canister.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>Additional tutorials covering more advanced programs and more detailed examples of how to use the basic building blocks are available in the <link xl:href="https://github.com/dfinity/examples">examples</link> repository and <link xl:href="../language-guide/motoko.xml"><emphasis>{proglang} Programming Language Guide</emphasis></link>.</simpara>
</article>