<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Developer Release Notes</title>
<date>2021-08-05</date>
</info>
<simpara>The {sdk-long-name} enables developers to develop applications to run on the Internet Computer.
The Motoko new programming language is bundled with the {sdk-long-name} to provide native support for creating tamper-proof software and open internet services.</simpara>
<simpara>The {sdk-short-name} provides everything you need to perform the following key tasks:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>Author canisters in Motoko and compile them to WebAssembly.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Simulate the Internet Computer network running locally on your development computer.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Deploy compiled programs as <link xl:href="../developers-guide/glossary.xml#g-canister">canisters</link>.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Interact with your application service using a command-line interface or through a web browser.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<simpara>The current release of the {sdk-long-name} is intended to introduce you to building applications that run on the Internet Computer and to provide access to the Internet Computer network for application testing, demonstration, and exploration..
The {sdk-long-name} should not be used for developing <emphasis>production applications</emphasis> at this time.</simpara>
</note>
<section xml:id="_known_issues_and_limitations">
<title>Known issues and limitations</title>
<simpara>This section covers any known issues or limitations that might affect how you work with the {sdk-short-name} in specific environments or scenarios.</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>Creating a new project displays errors or warnings.</simpara>
<simpara>By default, creating a new project installs node dependencies to support building a front-end for your project.</simpara>
<simpara>Depending on your environment, the installation of node dependencies might display errors or warnings generated by the <literal>npm</literal> package manager.</simpara>
<simpara>The errors and warnings issued by the <literal>npm</literal> package manager do not prevent you from successfully creating a new project and, in most cases, can be safely ignored.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_additional_questions_and_feedback">
<title>Additional questions and feedback</title>
<simpara>Joining the <link xl:href="https://forum.dfinity.org/">DFINITY Developer Forum</link> is an effective way to learn from community members, ask questions, solicit help from other developers, and provide insight and feedback about your experiences.</simpara>
<simpara>If you have questions that aren&#8217;t answered by the community, you might also want to check out <link xl:href="../developers-guide/troubleshooting.xml">Troubleshooting</link> topics for information about common issues, workarounds for known issues, or help troubleshooting warnings or errors.</simpara>
<simpara>For technical support, send email to <link xl:href="mailto:support@dfinity.org">DFINITY Support</link>.</simpara>
<simpara>A self-service Help Center of Knowledge Base articles will also be coming soon.</simpara>
</section>
</article>