<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Add a stylesheet</title>
<date>2021-08-05</date>
</info>
<simpara>Cascading stylesheets represent one of the most common ways to customize the user experience for an application.
This tutorial illustrates how to add a stylesheet when you use React to create a new front-end for your project.
If you already know how to add cascading stylesheets (CSS) to a React-based project, you can skip this tutorial.</simpara>
<note>
<simpara>This tutorial illustrates using the React framework to manage the Document Object Model (DOM) for your canister.
Because React has its own custom DOM syntax, you need to modify the webpack configuration to compile the front-end code, which is written in JSX. For more information about learning to use React and JSX, see <link xl:href="https://reactjs.org/docs/getting-started.html">Getting started</link> on the <link xl:href="https://reactjs.org/">React website</link>.</simpara>
</note>
<section xml:id="_before_you_begin">
<title>Before you begin</title>
<simpara>Before starting the tutorial, verify the following:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>You have <literal>node.js</literal> installed for front-end development and can install packages using <literal>npm install</literal> in your project.
For information about installing node for your local operating system and package manager, see the <link xl:href="https://nodejs.org/en/">Node</link> website.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>You have downloaded and installed the {sdk-short-name} package as described in <link xl:href="../../quickstart/local-quickstart.xml#download-and-install">Download and install</link>.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>You have installed the Visual Studio Code plugin for Motoko as described in <link xl:href="../../quickstart/local-quickstart.xml#install-vscode">Install the language editor plug-in</link> if you are using Visual Studio Code as your IDE.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>You have stopped any Internet Computer network processes running on the local
computer.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<simpara>Because of significant changes to the handling of HTTP requests and front-end assets, this tutorial requires you to use the {sdk-short-name} version <literal>0.7.0</literal> or later. For an overview of what&#8217;s changed, see this <link xl:href="../../http-middleware.xml">article</link>.</simpara>
</note>
</section>
<section xml:id="_create_a_new_project">
<title>Create a new project</title>
<simpara>To create a new project directory for your custom front-end application:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Open a terminal shell on your local computer, if you don’t already have one open.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Change to the folder you are using for your Internet Computer projects, if you are using one.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Verify that you have <literal>node.js</literal> installed locally, if necessary.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Create a new project by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">dfx new contacts</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Change to your project directory by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">cd contacts</programlisting>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_install_the_react_framework">
<title>Install the React framework</title>
<simpara>if you&#8217;ve never used React before, you might want to explore the <link xl:href="https://reactjs.org/tutorial/tutorial.html">Intro to React</link> tutorial or the <link xl:href="https://reactjs.org/">React website</link> before editing the front-end code.</simpara>
<simpara>To install required framework modules:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Install the React module by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">npm install --save react react-dom</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Install the required TypeScript language compiler loader by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">npm install --save-dev typescript ts-loader</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Install the required style loaders by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">npm install --save-dev style-loader css-loader</programlisting>
<simpara>If the <literal>npm install</literal> command reports a vulnerability, you might also want to run the <literal>npm audit fix</literal> command to attempt to fix the vulnerability reported before continuing.</simpara>
<note>
<simpara>As an alternative to installing these modules, you can edit the default <literal>package.json</literal> file to add dependencies for your project.</simpara>
</note>
<literallayout class="monospaced">Unresolved directive in my-contacts.adoc - include::example$add-stylesheet-package.json[]</literallayout>
<simpara>The version of the JavaScript agent in this example <literal>package.json</literal> file is <literal>0.9.2</literal>. In most cases, however, you would want to use the latest version of the agent available. When you create a new project, the <literal>dfx new</literal> command automatically retrieves the latest version of the JavaScript agent for you. You can also manually retrieve the latest version after creating a project by running the <literal>npm install --save @dfinity/agent</literal> command.</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_modify_the_default_program">
<title>Modify the default program</title>
<simpara>For this tutorial, you are going to modify the main program to with code that allows you to store and look up contact information.</simpara>
<simpara>To modify the default program:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the <literal>src/contacts/main.mo</literal> file in a text editor and delete the existing content.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Copy and paste the following sample code into the file:</simpara>
<programlisting role="copy" language="motoko" linenumbering="numbered">Unresolved directive in my-contacts.adoc - include::example$mycontacts/contacts.mo[]</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Save your changes and close the <literal>main.mo</literal> file to continue.</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_modify_the_front_end_files">
<title>Modify the front-end files</title>
<simpara>You are now ready to create a new front-end for your program.</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the webpack configuration file (<literal>webpack.config.js</literal>) in a text editor.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Modify the front-end entry to replace the default index.html with index.jsx.</simpara>
<programlisting language="js" linenumbering="unnumbered">entry: {
  // The frontend.entrypoint points to the HTML file for this build, so we need
  // to replace the extension to `.js`.
  index: path.join(__dirname, asset_entry).replace(/\.html$/, ".jsx"),
},</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Locate the commented example for the <literal>module</literal> key above the <literal>plugins</literal> section, then uncomment the following lines:</simpara>
<programlisting language="js" linenumbering="unnumbered">module: {
  rules: [
    { test: /\.(js|ts)x?$/, loader: "ts-loader" },
    { test: /\.css$/, use: ['style-loader','css-loader'] }
  ]
},</programlisting>
<simpara>These settings enable your program to use the <literal>ts-loader</literal> compiler and to import CSS files.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Save your changes and close the <literal>webpack.config.js</literal> file to continue.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Create a new file named <literal>tsconfig.json</literal> in the root directory for your project.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the <literal>tsconfig.json</literal> file in a text editor, then copy and paste the following into the file:</simpara>
<programlisting language="json" linenumbering="unnumbered">Unresolved directive in my-contacts.adoc - include::example$sample-tsconfig.json[]</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Save your changes and close the <literal>tsconfig.json</literal> file to continue.</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_add_a_stylesheet_to_your_project">
<title>Add a stylesheet to your project</title>
<simpara>You are now ready to create a new cascading stylesheet and add it to your project.</simpara>
<simpara>To add a stylesheet:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Change to the <literal>src/contacts_assets/assets</literal> directory.</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">cd src/contacts_assets/assets/</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the <literal>main.css</literal> file in a text editor and delete the existing content.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Define some style properties for the front-end.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, copy and paste the following sample styles into the file:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">Unresolved directive in my-contacts.adoc - include::example$mycontacts/mycontacts.css[]</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Save your changes and close the <literal>main.css</literal> file to continue.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Change to the <literal>src/contacts_assets/src</literal> directory.</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">cd ../src</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the default <literal>index.js</literal> file in a text editor and delete the existing content.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Copy and paste the following sample code into the <literal>index.js</literal> file:</simpara>
<programlisting language="react" linenumbering="unnumbered">Unresolved directive in my-contacts.adoc - include::example$mycontacts/mod-index.jsx[]</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Rename the modified <literal>index.js</literal> file as <literal>index.jsx</literal> by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">mv index.js index.jsx</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the default <literal>src/contacts_assets/src/index.html</literal> file in a text editor, then replace <literal>main.css</literal> as the stylesheet file name with <literal>mycontacts.css</literal> and update the <literal>body</literal> contents with <literal>&lt;div id="contacts"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>.</simpara>
<simpara>For example:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html lang="en"&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8" /&gt;
    &lt;meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width" /&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;contacts&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;base href="/" /&gt;

    &lt;link type="text/css" rel="stylesheet" href="main.css" /&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;main&gt;
      &lt;div id="contacts"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Navigate back to the root of your project directory.</simpara>
<simpara>For example:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">cd ../../..</programlisting>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_start_the_local_network">
<title>Start the local network</title>
<simpara>Before you can build the <literal>contacts</literal> project, you need to connect to the Internet Computer network either running locally in your development environment or running remotely on a subnet that you can access.</simpara>
<simpara>To start the network locally:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Open a new terminal window or tab on your local computer.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Start the Internet Computer network on your local computer by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">dfx start --background</programlisting>
<simpara>After the local Internet Computer network completes its startup operations, you can continue to the next step.</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_register_build_and_deploy_the_application">
<title>Register, build, and deploy the application</title>
<simpara>After you connect to the Internet Computer network running locally in your development environment, you can register, build, and deploy your application locally.</simpara>
<simpara>To deploy the application:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Check that you are still in the root directory for your project, if needed.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Register, build, and deploy your application by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">dfx deploy</programlisting>
<simpara>The <literal>dfx deploy</literal> command output displays information about the operations it performs.</simpara>
<simpara>Keep in mind that because you are running the Internet Computer locally, the identifiers displayed when you run the <literal>dfx deploy</literal> command are only valid on the local network.</simpara>
<simpara>To deploy canisters on an external Internet Computer network, you must connect to that network using the <literal>--network</literal> command-line option and a specific network name or address to register identifiers on that network.
For example, to deploy on the Internet Computer using the reserve network alias <literal>ic</literal>, you would run a command similar the following:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">dfx deploy --network=ic</programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Start the Webpack development server:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">npm start</programlisting>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_view_the_front_end">
<title>View the front-end</title>
<simpara>You can now access the front-end for the <literal>contacts</literal> program by entering the canister identifier for the assets canister in a browser.</simpara>
<simpara>To view the front-end:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Open a browser and navigate to the <literal><link xl:href="http://localhost:8080">http://localhost:8080</link></literal>.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Verify that you are prompted with a <emphasis role="strong">My Contacts</emphasis> form.</simpara>
<simpara>For example:</simpara>
<simpara><inlinemediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="mycontacts-form.png"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Sample front-end</phrase></textobject>
</inlinemediaobject></simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Create one or more test records by entering text in the Name, Address, and Email input fields and a number in the Phone input field, then clicking <emphasis role="strong">Add Contact</emphasis>.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Clear the form fields and type a contact name in the Lookup name field, then click <emphasis role="strong">Lookup</emphasis> to see the stored contact information.</simpara>
<simpara>Keep in mind that the <emphasis role="strong">Lookup name</emphasis> you type must be an exact match for the name of a contact you added.</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_modify_the_stylesheet_and_test_your_changes">
<title>Modify the stylesheet and test your changes</title>
<simpara>After viewing the Contacts application, you might want to make some changes.</simpara>
<simpara>To change stylesheet properties:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>Open the <literal>src/contacts_assets/public/mycontacts.css</literal> file in a text editor and modify its style settings.</simpara>
<simpara>For example, you might want to change the background color or style the input form.</simpara>
<simpara>You should see the changes update immediately in your open browser window.</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_modify_the_front_end_or_back_end_code">
<title>Modify the front-end or back-end code</title>
<simpara>If you want to explore further, you might want to experiment with modifying the front-end or back-end code for this tutorial.
For example, you might want try modifying the tutorial to do the following:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>Change the front-end code to clear the input fields after adding a new contact, for example, as part of an <literal>onClick</literal> event.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Change the Motoko program functions to do partial instead of exact string matching on the <literal>Name</literal> field. (You will need to run <literal>dfx deploy</literal> to test your changes on the local replica)</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Change the Motoko program to allow lookups based on a different field.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_stop_the_local_network">
<title>Stop the local network</title>
<simpara>After you finish experimenting with your program, you can stop the local Internet Computer network so that it doesn’t continue running in the background.</simpara>
<simpara>To stop the local network:</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>In the terminal that displays your webpack dev server, press Control-C to interrupt the development server.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Stop the Internet Computer network by running the following command:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">dfx stop</programlisting>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</article>